<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>trialr | Kristian Brock</title>
    <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/tags/trialr/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.kristianbrock.com/tags/trialr/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>trialr</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.kristianbrock.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>trialr</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/tags/trialr/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>trialr and escalation</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/post/trialr-and-escalation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/post/trialr-and-escalation/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;summary&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post sets out how two of my R packages, &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=trialr&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=escalation&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, will work together and grow in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;background&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=trialr&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Brock 2020b; Brock 2019)&lt;/span&gt; is a package I wrote to fit complex Bayesian clinical trial models using &lt;a href=&#34;https://mc-stan.org/&#34;&gt;Stan&lt;/a&gt;.
Because I generally work on early phase trials, and because early phase trials are generally predisposed to Bayesian methods, the package ended up containing quite a few dose-finding methods like CRM &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(O’Quigley, Pepe, and Fisher 1990)&lt;/span&gt; and EffTox &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Thall and Cook 2004)&lt;/span&gt;.
I initially added code to this package that would aid practical implementation of these methods, like conducting simulation studies and calculating future dose-paths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later I introduced the &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=escalation&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Brock 2020a)&lt;/span&gt; package, containing a more general range of dose-finding methods (i.e. not just those that require MCMC methods for model-fitting).
The beauty of &lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt; is that formalises the interface for dose-finding designs.
For instance, all methods recommend a dose through the &lt;code&gt;recommended_dose()&lt;/code&gt; function and distinguish between the need to stop or continue via the &lt;code&gt;continue()&lt;/code&gt; function.
This standard interface allows the elements of designs to become modules that can be arbitrarily combined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt; allows you to start with a CRM model, add behaviour to stop when a certain sample size is reached, but ensure that the recommended dose is evaluated in at least &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt; patients before stopping is permitted, all the while monitoring for excess toxicity at the lowest dose.
Because all of the modules obey the same interface, they can be combined in arbitrary ways to tailor the behaviour of designs.
The module that stops a trial when a target sample size is reached works whether it is preceded by a CRM design or BOIN design, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;do-we-need-both&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do we need both?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time &lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt; was released, there was quite a bit of overlap between &lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt;.
So do we need both?
Yes, and I will explain why!
Is &lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; now redundant?
Not at all, but it will become more focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt; went far further than &lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; in making dose-finding designs hot-swappable and customisable.
It makes sense that inferential tools like running simulations are offered in &lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt; so that comparing designs is easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; still has its place, however.
It takes care of fitting models to data using MCMC via Stan.
This is a reliable way of fitting complex (e.g. non-linear, multi-parameter) models when other methods struggle.
Henceforth, &lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; will focus only on Stan-based MCMC model-fitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt; will now use &lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; alongside dose-finding packages from other authors like &lt;code&gt;dfcrm&lt;/code&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Cheung 2013)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;code&gt;BOIN&lt;/code&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Yuan and Liu 2018)&lt;/span&gt; to support the broadest possible array of dose-escalation methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-might-this-look-in-future&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How might this look in future?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my near term goals is to add dose-response models to &lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; like Emax.
Dose-response modelling is a topic close to dose-finding trials but quite distinct from it.
When I add the Emax model, the Stan implementation will go in &lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt;.
If the Emax model stands to be useful as a dose-selection tool, then it can be added to support the usual methods in the &lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-situation-now&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The situation now&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently updated both packages on CRAN:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; is now at v0.1.5 at &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=trialr&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=trialr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt; is now at v0.1.4 at &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=escalation&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=escalation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;escalation&lt;/code&gt; now depends on &lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; to deliver Stan-MCMC implementations of CRM, EffTox, and the phase I method of &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Neuenschwander, Branson, and Gsponer (2008)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Brock2019&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brock, Kristian. 2019. “trialr: Bayesian Clinical Trial Designs in R and Stan.” &lt;em&gt;arXiv E-Prints&lt;/em&gt;, June, arXiv:1907.00161.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-escalation&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brock, Kristian. 2020a. &lt;em&gt;Escalation: Modular Approach to Dose Finding Clinical Trials&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=escalation&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=escalation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-trialr&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———. 2020b. &lt;em&gt;Trialr: Clinical Trial Designs in ’Rstan’&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=trialr&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=trialr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-dfcrm&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheung, Ken. 2013. &lt;em&gt;Dfcrm: Dose-Finding by the Continual Reassessment Method&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=dfcrm&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=dfcrm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Neuenschwander2008&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuenschwander, Beat, Michael Branson, and Thomas Gsponer. 2008. “Critical aspects of the Bayesian approach to phase I cancer trials.” &lt;em&gt;Statistics in Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 27: 2420–39. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/sim.3230&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/sim.3230&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-OQuigley1990&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O’Quigley, J, M Pepe, and L Fisher. 1990. “Continual Reassessment Method: A Practical Design for Phase 1 Clinical Trials in Cancer.” &lt;em&gt;Biometrics&lt;/em&gt; 46 (1): 33–48. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2307/2531628&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.2307/2531628&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Thall2004&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thall, PF, and JD Cook. 2004. “Dose-Finding Based on Efficacy-Toxicity Trade-Offs.” &lt;em&gt;Biometrics&lt;/em&gt; 60 (3): 684–93.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-BOIN&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yuan, Ying, and Suyu Liu. 2018. &lt;em&gt;BOIN: Bayesian Optimal Interval (Boin) Design for Single-Agent and Drug- Combination Phase I Clinical Trials&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=BOIN&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=BOIN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>trialr - Bayesian Clinical Trial Designs in R and Stan</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/trialr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/trialr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-this-publication&#34;&gt;About this publication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I became aware of Stan whilst working on some Bayesian clinical trial designs.
I recall using Monte Carlo integration to resolve six-dimensional integrals to estimate posterior means and thinking that there must be a better way.
In fact, there were probably many better ways.
However, I doubt any would be as good as Stan, a probabilistic programming language and Hamiltonion Monte Carlo Markov Chain sampler.
This manuscript is my first sole-author attempt at research.
It was particularly pleasing to implement James Wason and Shaun Seaman&#39;s augmented binary method, an approach that will surely feature strongly if we are to wean ourselves off information-light binary response variables.
&lt;code&gt;trial&lt;/code&gt; is on CRAN.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
