<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PhaseII | Kristian Brock</title>
    <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/tags/phaseii/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.kristianbrock.com/tags/phaseii/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>PhaseII</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.kristianbrock.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>PhaseII</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/tags/phaseii/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>PePS2</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/project/peps2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/project/peps2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PePS2 is a phase II trial of pembrolizumab in performance status 2 (PS2) non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients.
It is run by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/research/activity/mds/trials/crctu/&#34;&gt;Cancer Research UK Clinical Trials Unit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PePS2 is an important trial to me because I developed the analysis model as part of my PhD thesis and worked on the trial from almost the very beginning.
I published a trial design paper and am glad to say that the trial results are currently under peer review.
The investigators and I hope this trial will provide much-needed and much-sought evidence on the merits of giving this PD-L1 blockade drug to PS2 NSCLC patients&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;design&#34;&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I became involved in PePS2 shortly after joining the trials unit in 2014.
The trial called for a design that evaluated co-primary response and toxicity outcomes.
Naturally, this suggests a Bryant &amp;amp; Day optimal design.
However, published data in performance status 0 &amp;amp; 1 NSCLC patients showed that the PD-L1 tumour proportion score biomarker was strongly predictive of response.
There was also evidence that first-line patients did better than subsequent-line patients.
We expected each of these variables to remain predictive in the performance status 2 population and wanted to stratify the analysis by these variables.
Unfortunately, Bryant &amp;amp; Day&#39;s design assumes an homogeneous population so does not admit explanatory variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I happened to be working on a dose-finding trial at the time that used the EffTox design of Thall &amp;amp; Cook (2004) to appraise joint efficacy and toxicity rates at different doses of experimental agents.
It struck me on a cycle home that the EffTox design could be adjusted with variables reflecting PD-L1 and line-of-therapy status in place of dose to study our co-primary outcomes whilst adjusting for our putative predictive factors.
I worked up the design as part of my PhD, eventually published a design paper, and used the model to conduct a Bayesian analysis of the outcomes in a results manuscript that is currently in peer-review.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ibrutinib Plus Venetoclax in Relapsed/Refractory Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia - The CLARITY Study</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/clarity-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/clarity-results/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-this-publication&#34;&gt;About this publication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This publication is important to me because Clarity was my first successful grant application.
It is a simple trial with modest sample size but the results are absolutely amazing, with an iwCLL response rate of 89% and minimum disease negative status achieved in the peripheral blood of 53% of patients.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
