<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 | Kristian Brock</title>
    <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication_types/2/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication_types/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>2</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.kristianbrock.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication_types/2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pembrolizumab in patients with non-small-cell lung cancer of performance status 2 (PePS2) - a single arm, phase 2 trial</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/peps2-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/peps2-results/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-this-publication&#34;&gt;About this publication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I became involved in the PePS2 trial shortly after joining CRCTU in 2014.
I developed a Bayesian statistical method for this trial that would analyse co-primary efficacy and toxicity outcomes whilst adjusting for baseline covariates as a substantial part of my PhD thesis.
This publication is important to me because PePS2 became the first trial where I published a statistical design paper and results paper.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ibrutinib Plus Venetoclax in Relapsed/Refractory Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia - The CLARITY Study</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/clarity-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/clarity-results/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-this-publication&#34;&gt;About this publication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This publication is important to me because Clarity was my first successful grant application.
It is a simple trial with modest sample size but the results are absolutely amazing, with an iwCLL response rate of 89% and minimum disease negative status achieved in the peripheral blood of 53% of patients.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to design a dose-finding study using the continual reassessment method</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/crm-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/crm-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-this-publication&#34;&gt;About this publication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had been a trial statistician about 6 months when I attended an NIHR workshop on early phase trial methodology in 2014.
The topic of the day was the trials community&amp;rsquo;s over-reliance on rule-based dose-finding methods like 3+3.
This tutorial paper was produced by a group of attendees to promote model-based methods.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combination Lenalidomide and Azacitidine - A Novel Salvage Therapy in Patients Who Relapse After Allogeneic Stem-Cell Transplantation for Acute Myeloid Leukemia</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/viola-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/viola-results/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-this-publication&#34;&gt;About this publication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is important to me because Viola was the first dose-finding trial that I worked on.
It uses a CRM model to identify a dose of lenalidomide that is tolerable when given with azacitidine to AML and MDS patients.
This was also one of my first published sets of trial results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing the EffTox dose-finding design in the Matchpoint trial</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/matchpoint-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/publication/matchpoint-design/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-this-publication&#34;&gt;About this publication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my first first-author publication and a chapter in my PhD thesis.
Working with EffTox was great, but challenging at times.
The seamless phase I/II approach to dose-finding, where efficacy and toxicity outcomes guide dose selection, has never been more important in this era of targeted therapies in oncology.
However, the EffTox design and the suite of phase I/II methods in general have been relatively underutilised.
We hope this paper demonstrating our experiences with EffTox will inspire early phase trialists to look further than the 3+3.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
