<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Kristian Brock</title>
    <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.kristianbrock.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.kristianbrock.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The PePS2 Trial</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/project/peps2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/project/peps2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PePS2 is a phase II trial of pembrolizumab in performance status 2 (PS2) non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients.
It is run by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/research/activity/mds/trials/crctu/&#34;&gt;Cancer Research UK Clinical Trials Unit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PePS2 is an important trial to me because I developed the analysis model as part of my PhD thesis and worked on the trial from almost the very beginning.
I published a trial design paper and am glad to say that the trial results are currently under peer review.
The investigators and I hope this trial will provide much-needed and much-sought evidence on the merits of giving this PD-L1 blockade drug to PS2 NSCLC patients&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;design&#34;&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I became involved in PePS2 shortly after joining the trials unit in 2014.
The trial called for a design that evaluated co-primary response and toxicity outcomes.
Naturally, this suggests a Bryant &amp;amp; Day optimal design.
However, published data in performance status 0 &amp;amp; 1 NSCLC patients showed that the PD-L1 tumour proportion score biomarker was strongly predictive of response.
There was also evidence that first-line patients did better than subsequent-line patients.
We expected each of these variables to remain predictive in the performance status 2 population and wanted to stratify the analysis by these variables.
Unfortunately, Bryant &amp;amp; Day&#39;s design assumes an homogeneous population so does not admit explanatory variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I happened to be working on a dose-finding trial at the time that used the EffTox design of Thall &amp;amp; Cook (2004) to appraise joint efficacy and toxicity rates at different doses of experimental agents.
It struck me on a cycle home that the EffTox design could be adjusted with variables reflecting PD-L1 and line-of-therapy status in place of dose to study our co-primary outcomes whilst adjusting for our putative predictive factors.
I worked up the design as part of my PhD, eventually published a design paper, and used the model to conduct a Bayesian analysis of the trial outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results for PePS2 were published in March 2020 in Lancet Respiratory Medicine.
There are links below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The trialr package</title>
      <link>https://www.kristianbrock.com/project/trialr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.kristianbrock.com/project/trialr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; is an R package that implements Bayesian clinical trial design in &lt;a href=&#34;https://mc-stan.org/&#34;&gt;Stan&lt;/a&gt;, a modern enviroment for probabilistic programming that implements Hamiltonian Monte Carlo Markov Chain sampling.
Bayesian models are relatively abundant in early phase clinical trials where information is scarce and sensible inference is required practically from the moment the trial begins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;trialr&lt;/code&gt; implements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Contimual Reassessment Method (CMR) for toxicity-based dose-finding;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the time-to-event CRM for late-onset toxicity in dose-finding;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the EffTox for toxicity- and efficacy-based dose-finding;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wason &amp;amp; Seaman&#39;s Augmented Binary method for fusing continuous and binary outcomes in phase II;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a hierarchical model of binary responses on related subgroups;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;trialr is available on CRAN and is listed on my GitHub page.
There is a manuscript currently under peer-review (pre-print linked below) and it has been used to analyse outcomes in a forthcoming set of clinical trial results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CRAN listing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/trialr/index.html&#34;&gt;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/trialr/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/brockk/trialr&#34;&gt;https://github.com/brockk/trialr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://brockk.github.io/trialr/&#34;&gt;https://brockk.github.io/trialr/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
